If you're not living under a rock, you
probably know the man next to me, Kanye West.
But as prolific as life as
the man as Kanye West lives,
I'm not here today to talk about his music,
or his shoes, or anything going on in the media.
What I'm going to talk about is the new device that
Kanye West has released in his newest business venture, the Stem Player.
Kanye and his new device, the Stem Player,
could become a major disruptor in the music industry
and really cause a lot of problems for a lot of the
labels out there that hold a lot of the power in that industry.
But before we get into how
Kanye is disrupting the music industry,
let's first talk about the device itself, the Stem Player.
So if you haven't seen
or heard of the Stem Player,
essentially it's a circular device that can
take a song that you upload to it,
and it will break down its musical components so that you
can manipulate the song to sound however you want it to.
Essentially, it breaks it down into four key components,
meaning the vocals, the bass, the
drums, and any samples the song contains.
It also adds special features to where you
can make parts of a song faster, slower,
or repeats different parts of a song in a loop.
The concept of the device itself is revolutionary,
because basically you can produce and manipulate your
own remixes or even songs themselves from the device.
So although this is a revolutionary tool for producers,
how is this really shaking up the music industry?
Well, for starters, after announcing
the exclusivity of the device,
Kanye sold three million dollars worth of Stem Players.
This comes after an announcement saying that
Kanye was only going to drop Donda 2
specifically and exclusively on the Stem Player.
Because of that announcement, this caused a
ton of fans or people who are just
fans of music in general to
go out and buy the Stem Player,
because they don't want to miss out on
hearing this exclusive project that Kanye's dropping.
Fans were even more serious to go and buy the
Stem Player after hearing that Kanye West apparently turned down
a 100 million dollar deal from Apple.
All this hype built around this exclusive project
that would be dropping on the Stem Player
ultimately led to that three million dollar sales figure.
To essentially put in perspective how
brilliant of a move this was,
to achieve three million dollars in streaming revenue,
you would have had to have
cumulated 500 million streams for this album.
Even though these sales figures sound great for Kanye,
why do the labels care
about this? He's just one artist.
Why does him taking
his music off their platform and putting
it on his own so important to them?
And how is it disrupting the music industry?
To see how this really shake things up,
I'm going to break down what the
traditional music streaming business model looks like.
Essentially, artists make music for the label,
then labels will lease out the music streaming platforms,
and then the streaming platforms will
give that music available to its users
in exchange for money, which
that money is then kicked back
to the labels that is then
hopefully would trickle down to the artists.
Because in this model, the artists
have to go through the label
and the label itself to get the music
they want. And that's why this is so important.
And the streaming platforms just to
deliver their product to the users,
they're not going to get as much money in return,
whether they had their own platform
that they could release their music.
This is completely different than what the
stem player model is trying to accomplish.
If we take Kanye, for example, as the artist,
he owns the platform that he's distributing the music on.
So essentially, he just uploads
his music to his own platform,
which is the stem player.
And then the users of the platform already
paid up front $200 for the stem player,
and the money will get kicked back.
And so the money will get kicked
back directly to Kanye as the artist
or anybody else involved in the company.
No going through a streaming
platform, no going through labels.
All the money will get
kicked back directly to the artist.
Well, you may be thinking to yourself,
great, Kanye has a better business model,
but how is he going
to be labels and streaming platforms
that have been set up for the
business with all these customers for years?
Well, if you've been paying attention to
anything going on in modern media culture,
you can see that Kanye is a master marketer.
His documentary is coming out at
the same time as this exclusive album.
Everybody that watches Netflix and those streaming platforms
are already talking about him and noticing him
because his documentary is out on the streaming platform.
He also is always in the media,
whether it's for something they're trying to
portray him as being good or bad.
But either way, him just being
in the media for whatever story
is just going to get the common people,
whether they enjoy music or not,
to know and hear his name.
Plus, if you're a fan of Kanye,
you're probably following him on social media.
And if you follow his Instagram,
嘻
clearly is someone that you have to keep up
with if you want to see what he posts.
He'll pretty much post a series of Instagram posts,
and then we'll take them down after a few days.
So if you're not constantly paying
attention to what the guy's doing,
you're going to miss what he's posting and
keeping up to date with what he does.
On top of all that, Kanye
is really the only artist out there
that is producing live updates of his
album in person, in front of everybody.
If you look over interviews over the years,
you can see that Kanye is
a big fan of Steve Jobs,
and he kind of developed this concept that he
learned from Steve Jobs as being the CEO of Apple,
that the one reason that makes Apple so successful
is they test their products in front of everybody.
They want people to view and provide as much feedback
and see a live demonstration of the
products as they're making them and developing them.
Kanye essentially took on that idea
of producing things in front of everybody
and getting live feedback when it comes to his albums.
He's been doing it far earlier than people remember.
He started the first listening
party during the Life of Pablo
era back in 2016.
Basically, he wants to hear
the way it sounds in stadium.
He wants to see the expression and
emotion on as many faces as possible.
He wants to see the reaction on social media
as he continues to make updates to
the album until it's in its final form.
If you look at the Life
of Pablo, Kanye's album from 2016,
he's not making any more changes to it.
But back when that was dropped,
so many different changes were made
to it over and over again,
even after he dropped it on Tidal,
and then it was released on normal streaming platforms.
He carried this process into,
what was probably the most hyped
up and anticipated album of 2021,
which was Donda,
with the several listening parties that
he conducted in Atlanta and Chicago.
Pretty much even at these listening parties,
Kanye didn't even say a word into the mic.
He just stood around in the stadium and
let people listen to his album in its entirety.
At the first listening party,
the album wasn't even finished in time,
but Kanye is just sitting there in the stadium listening,
trying to get that feedback so he
knows what to go and make changes to.
Developing the same concept that Steve Jobs,
applied to the tech at Apple.
Because no artist is presenting their
albums in this kind of form,
where people are going to conjoin into
a stadium and just spend their time
listening to an artist's album
that hasn't even released yet,
it drums up so much hype and marketing
around the album and for Kanye as an artist.
That in addition to all the other factors,
it's why Kanye's marketing plan is so
genius and how he can drive $3 million
worth of sales for his own platform.
So is Kanye going to be
the only artist with his own platform?
Probably not.
This is only the beginning of opening up
Pandora's box when it comes to the album.
It's only the beginning of the album
when it comes to the exclusivity of music
and artists retaining the rights
for everything that they have.
Time and time again,
artists have just been screwed over by the music industry,
not getting enough kickbacks and enough
revenue from the music that they create.
In addition to the development of NFTs and artists
being able to sell their music as an exclusive asset,
developing their own platform,
Kanye is just the first to do so.
Of course, if Kanye wanted to,
he could drop other artists
projects on the stem player platform,
or other artists are going to
go out and create their own.
This would be no more label contracts.
Artists would retain all the exclusive
rights to everything that they produce,
and they would receive all the money for it.
Not to mention when you have your own platform,
you get to choose what to do with it.
You don't have to abide by
any rules by a big tech company.
In the case of Kanye's shoes,
he's constantly updating,
adding and dropping songs from the
stem player platform day by day.
So is this overall Kanye's goal for this?
Well, I think it's part of it.
He wants his exclusive rights for all his music,
and he wants his own platform to be able to
spread his voice and do what he wants with it.
But I also think that there's
another bigger thing at stake here.
Apple offered him a $100 million deal,
as so it says in the news.
Well, Kanye turned that down.
My thinking is Kanye wants to develop and
produce as many albums for himself or other artists
on his stem player platform to
drive up sales for the stem player
that would outpace the $100 million
he would have made with Apple.
Therefore saying,
I don't really need the labels.
I'm going to do what I want on my platform.
So is this the best thing for the music industry?
Are people really going to
want to have to do this?
Are people going to want to have to
go get their music from all these different locations
and platforms to listen to their favorite artists?
Not necessarily,
but as things are becoming more decentralized and
artists are wanting to take their rights back
for what they put out and produce,
pretty much if you're a big fan of an
artist and you really want to listen to their music,
you're more than likely probably going to spend
the money to be on their exclusive platform
and hear what they have to say.
What Kanye is doing with the stem player is only
the first big step for decentralization in the music industry,
and it's only going to affect all
artists, labels, and streaming platforms to come.
If you decided to watch the
whole video, thanks so much for staying.
If you enjoyed it, please comment
down below your favorite Kanye West song
and leave a subscribe on the channel.
We've got great more business news,
tech news, crypto news coming your way.
And be sure to check out the School
of Hard Knocks on TikTok, Instagram, and Facebook.
Thank you.